last day of סוטה, Sotah, דף מ"ט Daf Mem Tet 49, and
we pick up at the very bottom of מ"ח עמוד ב'. Mem
Chet Amud Bet. Let's go from the two dots, four lines from
the
bottom. Okay. ופסקו אנשי אמנה Upasku Anshei Amana or,. Anyway, this is
about how everything has gone to pot, so it's a basic theme
of the end of מסכת סוטה. Masechet Sotah. That's a rough, okay,
and that was
from משחרב בית המקדש. Mishecharav Beit Hamikdash. Okay. אמר
רבי יצחק אלו בני אדם שהם מאמינים בהקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Rabbi
Yitzchak Elu Bnei Adam Shehem Maaminim BaKadosh Baruch Hu, people that believe
in God, have true faith. דתניא, Detanya, רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר כל
מי שיש לו פת בסלו ואומר מה אוכל למחר אינו אלא מקטני
אמנה. Rabbi Eliezer HaGadol Omer Kol Mi Sheyesh Lo Pas Besalo Veomer
Ma Ochal Lemachar, Eino Ela Mikatnei Amana. Anybody that's got bread in
their basket and is worried about how they're going to make money
for tomorrow, how they're going to bring in the bread tomorrow,
means this is a person that has lack of full faith. You
have to just trust that God will provide for tomorrow.
We talked about ברית המלח Brit HaMelach or אמוראים, Amora'im, it's funny
because you see ראשונים Rishonim exactly.
והיי
דאמר רבי אליעזר מה דכתיב כי מי בז ליום קטנות, Vahai Deamar
Rabbi Eliezer Mai Dichtiv Ki Mi Baz Leyom Katnut, who is it
who did like dismissed, denigrate, whatever, right,
a day of smallness? מי גרם לצדיקים שיתבזבז שולחנם לעתיד לבוא, Mi
Garam Latzaddikim Sheitbazez Shulchanam Leatid Lavo,
who causes the righteous that their table will be like treated lowly,
will not be full in the world to come? קטנות שהיה בהם,
Katnut Shehaya Bahem,
so these are righteous people but they still didn't have full faith.
שלא האמינו בהקדוש ברוך הוא, Shelo Heeminu BaKadosh Baruch Hu, they didn't
have full faith in God. So therefore it's, so because they didn't
have faith for God that God would provide for the next day
and they had worry about, they had some anxiety about that, about
how they were going to feed themselves the next day, so that
in the way of מדה כנגד מדה, Mida Kneged Mida, their table
is not fully full לעתיד לבוא. Leatid Lavo.
And at least we're talking about the בית, Bayit, right, בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, so let's fit in, it's a number of times that
משחרב בית המקדש.
Mishecharav
Beit Hamikdash.
Yeah, he was actually talking about the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Talking
about the second בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Right.
So I'm saying the timing, right, the פסוקים, Psukim, yeah. Okay. רבא
אמר אלו קטני בני רשעי ישראל. Rava Amar Elu Katnei Bnei Reshei
Yisrael. Interesting, he switches the focus, the shift. These are actually no,
the young, the children
of wicked people. Okay, and what happens, so they basically these are
people that died when they were young, okay, and presumably because of
a punishment to the parent, to the father for his wicked deeds.
Okay, so what does it mean כי מי בז ליום קטנות? Ki
Mi Baz Leyom Katnut? שמבזין דינא דאביהם לעתיד לבוא, Shemevazin Dina Deavihem
Leatid Lavo, that they
downplay the judgment that's deserving,
that the father's deserving in the future time. אומרים לפניו, Omrim Lefanav,
they say before Him: רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam, מאחר שאתה
עתיד ליפרע מהם, Meachar Sheata Atid Lipara Mehem,
so if You were going to pay them back in full for
their sin in the world to come, למה הקהית שיניהם בם, Lama
Hikisat Shinehem Bam,
so why did You already blunt their teeth, meaning why did You
cause us to die? So the fact that we died when we
were small children, that should be partial payback for our fathers for
the sins that they have done. Okay, alright, so not exactly at
all fitting into the larger theme here and it's actually an interesting
twist on it, right, because normally we sort of say like we're
always happy to see the wicked being punished, and
but here actually there's a certain sense of compassion when people lose
small children, so at least that should be some, even if they're
wicked, some atonement לעתיד לבוא. Leatid Lavo.
I'm sorry, isn't it meaning that they have a question?
Right, they challenge God. God, how can You desire to pay them
back in full given that we died and we have suffered
in this life? Okay. אמר רבי אלעאי בר יברכיה
אלמלא תפלתו של דוד היו כל ישראל מוכרי ריבב. Amar Rabbi Ilai
bar Yevarcha Ilmale Tifilato Shel David Hayu Kol Yisrael Mochrei Rivav. Were
it not for the prayers of דוד, David, all of the Jewish
people would be reduced to selling like grease, so stuff that a
seller's got to sell, but who wants to be selling it? Okay,
so usually it's only the poor who sell it. שנאמר, Sheneemar, שיתה
ה' מורה להם, Shisa Hashem Mora Lahem, God place for them teacher
or be a teacher for them. So what does that mean? So
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says the following: לעיל מיניה כתיב
כי לא לנצח ישכח אביון, Le'eil minei dichtiv Ki Lo Lanetzach Yishachach
Evyon, God You will not forget, this is the beginning of the
small lines in רש"י, Rashi, You will not for eternity forget the
poor, תקות עניים תאבד לעד, Tikvat Aniyim Tovad La'ad, the longing, the
hope of the lowly shall never be lost forever. שיתה ה' מורה
להם, Shisa Hashem Mora Lahem, so this is talking about obviously the
poor. שיתה ה' מורה להם, Shisa Hashem Mora Lahem, תן להם מרות,
Ten Lahem Marut, so he's reading מורה Mora as give them some
type of mastery, some type of status, okay, לאותם עניים עושר, Leosam
Aniyim Osher, give them some type of wealth, שהרי גוים נוהגים בהם.
Sheharei Goyim Nohagim Bahem. כבוד, kavod, וידעו הגויים שהם אנוש ואינם אלוהות,
veyede'u hagoyim shehem enosh ve'einam elohut, so that the בני אנוש Bnei
Enosh should know that they're just men, the אנוש, Enosh, שאין כל
הכבוד והגדולה שלהם. she'ein kol hakavod vehagedulah shelahem. So God, please give
even to the lowly that we are so lowly, don't forget us
for forever, give us some type of mastery in this world. Okay,
so exactly not exactly clear what this has to do with אמונה
emunah here, but maybe because it has to do with anxiety about
whether a person would be able to provide for themselves. So David's
prayer, or maybe it's a sense about the, I don't know, about
the fact that we just spoke about like suffering in this world,
I really don't get exactly the tie-in. Anyway, ואמר רבי אלעא בר
בר יבחרייא, Ve'amar Rabbi Ila'i bar bar Yavchaya, unless it was the
same רבי אלעא בר יבחרייא, Rabbi Ila'i bar Yavchaya, maybe that was
the tie-in, was there a רבי אלעא בר יבחרייא? Rabbi Ila'i bar
Yavchaya?
No. Secondly he, second... yeah, but what I don't understand why we
brought in the first mention of him, what exactly the tie-in was.
Okay. ואמר רבי אלעא בר יבחרייא, Ve'amar Rabbi Ila'i bar Yavchaya, למאי
צלותא דחבקוק, Lemai tzlosa de'Chabakuk, what's to the prayer of חבקוק? Chabakuk?
הבט תלמידי חכמים שמתכסים בטלית אחת. Habat talmidei chachamim shemiskasim betalis achas.
So again, I guess the theme here is about prayers leading to
being, you know, leading to people not being reduced to poverty in
this world, so that has something to do with I guess this
idea again of like having full faith in God, that even if
things look like they are like you know very desperate and you
know
and no hope in terms of somebody's financial well-being, ultimately God can
provide. So I guess that's the tie-in. Okay, so what's to the
prayer of חבקוק? Chabakuk? Then two sages would be so poor, תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim scholars, that they would be reduced to covering themselves
with one garment, ועוסקים בתורה, ve'oskim baTorah, and they would,
and in that process learning תורה, Torah, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, as on the
one hand you could be framed as a degree of devotion to
learning תורה Torah that even though they're shivering and they just have
one garment to cover them, but it's also talking about the poverty
they would be reduced to, and because of his prayer they were
saved from that poverty. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, the verse says, השם שמעתי שמעך
יראתי, Hashem shamati shimacha yarasi, I have heard your, you know what,
your report, your message. יראתי השם פעלך, Yarasi Hashem po'alcha,
I have seen your doings. בקרב שנים חייהו. Bekerev shanim chayeihu.
So in the midst of years give them life, give it life.
What does that mean? אל תקרא בקרב שנים אלא בקירוב שנים, Al
tikra bekerev shanim ela bekiruv shnayim, in the very in the midst
of two people so who are sitting and learning, חייהו, chayeihu, give
them some type of חיה, chaya, give them some type of חיים,
chayim, give them some type of a פרנסה. parnasa. Okay, make it
better for them. So that and that's the idea that ties into
the תורה Torah sages because who are the ones who are hearing
God's message and who are seeing God's doings? Those that are studying
תורה. Torah. So those that are studying תורה, Torah, give them some
type of a life, give them a פרנסה. parnasa. Okay, ואמר רבי
אלעא בר יבחרייא, Ve'amar Rabbi Ila'i bar Yavchaya, שני תלמידי חכמים המהלכים
בדרך ואין ביניהם דברי תורה. Shnei talmidei chachamim hamahalchim baderech ve'ein beineihem
divrei Torah. So I guess now that we're talking about two תורה
Torah sages, so two תורה Torah scholars that are going on the
way and they're not talking in תורה, Torah, ראויים להישרף באש, re'uyim
lehisharef ba'esh, are deserving to be burned by a fire. שנאמר, She'ne'emar,
ויהי המה הולכים הלוך ודבר, vayehi heima holchim haloch vedaber, this is
by אלישע Elisha and אליהו, Eliyahu, they were going and talking, והנה
רכב אש, vehinei rechev esh, behold a chariot of fire. So if
and so they weren't hurt by it. So the reason they weren't
hurt is because they would have been deserving of the chariot of
fire had they not been talking of תורה. Torah. Okay, טעמא דאיכא
דיבור הא ליכא דיבור ראויים להישרף. Ta'ama de'ika dibur ha leika dibur
re'uyim lehisharef. Fine.
If they had not been talking, they'd be deserving of burning up.
ואמר רבי אלעא בר יבחרייא, Ve'amar Rabbi Ila'i bar Yavchaya, שני תלמידי
חכמים, shnei talmidei chachamim, that's רבי אלעא בר יבחרייא, Rabbi Ila'i bar
Yavchaya, two תורה Torah sages, הדרים בעיר אחת ואין, hadarim be'ir achas
ve'ein, oh no it's all רבי אלעא בר יבחרייא, Rabbi Ila'i bar
Yavchaya, oh it's all him, it's all him. Okay, fine.
So he's the one about the two תורה Torah sages covering with
a
טלית talis and חבקוק'ס Chabakuk's prayer provided for them, two תורה Torah
sages talking in תורה, Torah, and now we have two תורה Torah
sages so you know even the image of the טלית talis speaks
about a real sense of you know intimacy and you know and
like sort of dedication you know obviously to תורה Torah and therefore
connection to one another in that pursuit. So that's a little bit
played off here in the opposite scenario. So שני תלמידי חכמים הדרים
בעיר אחת, shnei talmidei chachamim hadarim be'ir achas, two תורה Torah sages
that are living in one city, ואין נוחים זה לזה בהלכה, ve'ein
nochim zeh lazeh bahalacha, and they're not sort of like a you
know a gracious towards one another, pleasant to one another when it
comes to matters of תורה Torah and הלכה. halacha. You know, one
says, "Well, I don't know, why don't you ask the other rabbi,
you know, you should speak to him as well."
You know, when the discourse is very...
exactly, exactly.
So you know so if they do not if there's not some
reciprocal type of respect and conversation going on between them, the opposite
of the image before, אחד מת ואחד גולה. echad meis ve'echad goleh.
In the end one will die and one will go into exile
or a similar fate. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, לנוס שמה רוצח, lanus shama rotze'ach,
what's the unit house for? To run to there a murderer אשר
ירצח את רעהו בבלי דעת, asher yirtzach es re'eihu bevli da'as, that
will kill his friend without knowledge. ואין דעת אלא תורה, Ve'ein da'as
ela Torah, knowledge means תורה, Torah, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, נדמו עמי מבלי הדעת,
nidmu ami mibli hada'as, my nation is silent because with lack of
knowledge. So I guess if you're silent it means you're not learning
תורה. Torah. So anyway so if they're מבלי דעת, mibli da'as, if
there's no תורה Torah being shared between the two of you, then
one will die and the other will go into exile.
ואין נוחים זה לזה בהלכה, Ve'ein nochim zeh lazeh bahalacha, meaning like
you can still share... without תורה Torah but like to be very
mean about it.
Yeah, I guess so. Maybe maybe it's even another stage,
maybe אינו נוח זה לזה בהלכה eino noach ze la-ze ba-halacha means
you don't even have any you know you're so you're so much
at war with one another you can't even talk about, you know,
you can't have any discourse. Yeah.
Who is this Rabbi Eliyahu Ben?
I don't know.
Yeah, I have
no idea.
His father's name, his father's name is May God Bless You.
Okay.
Okay, so I have no idea. I have no idea. אמר רבי
יהודה בר בריה דרבי חייא, Amar Rabbi Yehuda bar breih de-Rabbi Chiya,
כל תלמיד חכם העוסק בתורה מתוך הדחק, kol talmid chacham ha-osek ba-Torah
mi-toch ha-dachak, so now we're back to Torah sages learning without, you
know, in poverty and again the whole thing of אנשי אמנה, anshei
emuna,
so any Torah sage that learns תורה Torah out of a, you
know, some from straits, without,
you know,
in improvisation, תפלתו נשמעה, tefilato nishma'at,
his prayer will be heard. So before we said that David had
a prayer, Chabakkuk had a prayer, here this person's in himself, his
prayers are heard. Whatever the prayers are for, whether they're for better
פרנסה parnassa or anything, תפלתו נשמעה, tefilato nishma'at, his prayers are heard.
שנאמר, shene'emar, כי עם בציון ישב בירושלים, ki am be-Tziyon yeshev bi-Yerushalayim,
because a nation in Zion will dwell in Jerusalem, בכו לא תבכה,
bacho lo tivke, it will no longer cry, חנון יחנך, chanon yachnecha,
they will, God will show them grace, לקול זעקך כשמעתו ענך. le-kol
za'akecha ke-shom'ato anacha.
To the voice of your crying out when He God hears, He
answered them. So, so as soon as they cry out, God will
answer them. וכתיב בתריה, u-ketiv batreih, ונתן לכם ה' לחם צר ומים
לחץ, ve-natan lachem Hashem lechem tzar u-mayim lachatz, and there, and how
do we know that this is talking about people that are studying
out of privation? Because the next verse is that there you are,
you have very little bread and very little water, and nevertheless as
soon as you call out, God answers them.
לחם צר ומים לחץ,
lechem
tzar u-mayim lachatz, but as it, I know, I, yeah. I don't
know. I don't know what to tell you. But he's reading it
not as God responding to you, but as that was the situation
you were in and that's why God listens to you, because you
have that privation and you're studying תורה. Torah. Okay. So, okay. רבי
אבהו אומר, Rabbi Abbahu omer, משביעין אותו מזיו שכינה. masbi'in oto mi-ziv
Shechina.
Now of course the problem is is that on the one hand,
right, we talk about having אמונה, emuna, but I guess to some
degree there's a problem here that we're looking around and we're seeing
that people, you know, do have it tough. And you know, we
started by framing it as somebody who has bread, פתו בסלו pito
be-salo and is worried about what they're going to eat the next
day. But you know, there are people that actually do have a
hard time providing for themselves. So on the one hand we sort
of speak about David and Chabakkuk maybe saying like, oh, you know,
things would have been even worse, I don't know, or maybe saying
have faith, ultimately God will answer. And here we're saying, you know,
God will answer your prayers, but like it doesn't always, I mean
again that's always sort of the un-answered question, doesn't always work out
that way. So here the answer is you know what, they get
sustenance from God's presence, even if they don't get it from the
food on the table. So that's how God provides for them. Okay.
So he says, משביעין אותו מזיו שכינה, masbi'in oto mi-ziv Shechina, שנאמר,
shene'emar, והיו עיניך ראות את מוריך. ve-hayu einecha ro'ot et morecha. Your
eyes will see your teachers.
So that's part of that whole פרשה parsha that God will answer
them. So how does God answer you? By experiencing God's presence, that'll
sustain you. ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan, אף אין הפרגוד ננעל
בפניו, af ein ha-pargod nin'al be-fanav,
the heavenly gates or the curtain is not sealed before them in
terms of I guess again their prayers.
So שנאמר, shene'emar, ולא יכנף עוד מוריך. ve-lo yikanef od morecha.
Your teacher will no longer be like, you know, under a garment,
like covered from you. So God will no longer be covered from
you, you'll have that direct experience of God. So basically even if
it doesn't provide for you food on the table, you know, the
spiritual experience itself
is, you know, hopefully sustains a person. Okay, so that was the
קטני אמנה katnei emuna from the time of the destruction of בית
המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash. Yes.
Moshe when he goes up he's not eating anything.
Oh, that's a nice point. Right. Moshe doesn't have to eat because
he's in God's presence. Okay.
I mean, there are these people that basically these ascetics and these,
you know, monks or whatever that do seem able to like just
completely devote themselves to a spiritual life and actually sustain themselves on
very
little, you
know.
So, alright. Now, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר משום רבי יהושע, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer mishum Rabbi Yehoshua, מיום שחרב בית המקדש, mi-yom
she-charav Beis Ha-Mikdash, he says there is no day that does not
have in it some element of curse. Okay. So, אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, בכל יום ויום מרובה קללתו משל חבירו. be-chol yom va-yom meruba
klalato mi-shel chaveiro. Not only that, every if you wanted the a
clear statement about ירידת הדורות, yeridas ha-doros, every single day the degree
of curse increases from the day before. Every day is worse than
the previous day. שנאמר, shene'emar, as the פסוק pasuk says, בבקר תאמר
מי יתן ערב ובערב תאמר מי יתן בקר. ba-boker tomar mi yiten
erev u-va-erev tomar mi yiten boker. In the morning you'll say who
will give evening and in the evening you'll say who will give
morning. הי בוקר? Hai boker? So when it's evening and you're longing
for morning, which morning are you longing for? אילימא בוקר דלמחר? Ilima
boker de-lemachar?
The coming morning? מי ידע מאי הוי? mi yada mai havi? So
you don't know, maybe tomorrow will be worse, right? But maybe it'll
be better, but maybe it'll be worse. So I know, it's funny,
obviously in the פסוק pasuk it's like you're always hoping that the
future will be better, you know, past experience is what is it?
Is no
prediction... But the
Gemara says no, that doesn't make sense, maybe tomorrow will be worse.
So, אלא דחליף, ella dechalif, you mean the past morning. When it's
night, you say if only it was yesterday morning. Yesterday morning things
weren't as bad as they are tonight. So,
אלא דחליף. ella dechalif. So you see that every single passing moment
you wish it was the moment before. So every it's always getting
worse by the day.
ואלא עלמא אמאי מקיים? ve'ella alma amai mikayeim? So if the world
if things are getting so worse and the קללה kelala is getting
worse, what keeps the world going? Okay, which is interesting because like
it didn't say that like the Torah is lacking, you know, the
קללה kelala meaning I don't it's not exactly clear, right? Like why
is the קללה kelala getting worse? Because there's no בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, so it's a natural you know reality of the absence of
God's presence? Or is it are things continuing to get worse? Presumably
the question אמאי מקיים, amai mikayeim, what is the what's the good
deeds that keep it going, reflects the idea that if you're going
to say every day gets worse in terms of the you know
our well-being, that must be a reflection of or some type of
you know of of punishment for or reflection of the fact that
our deeds are continuing to get worse. Because the whole point of
the whole you know המשנה, mishnah, the whole end of this פרק,
perek, is that the deeds are getting worse. So if the every
day is increasing the קללה, kelala, it means that our deeds are
also getting worse every single day. So if every single day our
deeds are worse, what deeds you know what by what merit do
does things keep on going? ואלא עלמא אמאי מקיים? Ve'ella alma amai
mikayeim? By what merit does the world keep on going? אקדושה דסידרא
A'Kedusha DeSidra ויהא
שמיה רבא דאגדתא. ve'Yehei Shmei Rabba de'Agadata. Now this is very interesting,
right? Because this is like the Gemara you know like you know
like one of the few places that these תפילות tefillos are explicitly
addressed. And here it's saying that this sustains the world even when
everything is going to pot and all of our deeds are going
downhill, this keeps things going. Now what's what is קדושה דסידרא? Kedusha
DeSidra? קדושה דסידרא Kedusha DeSidra is after, you know, אשרי, Ashrei, it's
the ובא לציון U'va LeTziyon where you say קדוש קדוש Kadosh Kadosh
and ויהא, ve'yehei, yeah, and ברוך שם, Baruch Shem, but apparently that's
at least what apparently how this is identified. You know, ברוך שם
כבוד Baruch shem kvod etc. And יהא שמיה
רבא Yehei Shmei Rabba of what do you call it? I know
it's it's קדיש, Kaddish, but דאגדתא de'agadata after they would learn some
אגדתא agadata and the reason specifically mentions אגדתא agadata is it would
be a teaching that everybody could participate in. So that's basically what
רש״י Rashi says. So let's read the רש״י, Rashi, very important רש״י
Rashi here. So רש״י Rashi says,
אקדושה דסידרא, A'Kedusha DeSidra, about twenty lines on the bottom of the
first column. So he says, סדר קדושה שלא תקנוה אלא שיהו כל
ישראל עוסקין בתורה בכל יום דבר מועט. Seder Kedusha shelo tiknuha ela
sheyehu kol Yisrael oskin baTorah bechol yom davar mu'at. So everybody, it's
again a way that everybody participates in some basic merit. I don't
know what happened to קריאת שמע, Kriyas Shema, but okay. But anyway,
everybody is learning a little bit of תורה, Torah, okay, בכל יום
דבר מועט, bechol yom davar mu'at, שאומר קריאתו, she'omer kriyaso, so you
read the פסוקים, pesukim, ותרגומו. ve'targumo. Now that's an interesting point. Why
didn't they just say the קדושה Kedusha of חזרת הש״ץ? Chazaras HaShatz?
If you're in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei for the קדושה Kedusha of
ובא לציון, U'va LeTziyon, presumably you do of חזרת הש״ץ. Chazaras HaShatz.
But this has it in translation, and the and the Aramaic, although
we don't understand it all the time, was the vernacular. So it
meant that everybody was saying the קדיש Kaddish and was actually learning
a little bit. They were learning a translation of a פסוק. pasuk.
So it was תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah together with קדושת השם. Kedushas
Hashem. Okay? So ותרגומו והם כעוסקין בתורה, ve'targumo veheim ke'oskin baTorah, וכיון
שנהגו בכל ישראל בתלמידים ובעמי הארץ, vekeivan shenahagu bechol Yisrael betalmidim uve'amei
ha'aretz, and it's also something that brings everybody together, it doesn't create
a hierarchy, and it's a minimum thing that everybody is doing. ויש
כאן שנים קדושת השם ותלמוד תורה. veyeish kan shnayim Kedushas Hashem veTalmud
Torah. חביבה. Chaviva. וכן יהא שמיה רבא מבורך שאומרים אחר הגדה. Vechein
Yehei Shmei Rabba Mevorach she'omerim achar agada. Same idea, it's אגדתא, agadata,
it's a type of a תורה Torah that's accessible to everybody, שדרשן
דורש ברבים בכל שבת. shedarshan doreish berabbim bechol Shabbos. On Shabbos it
would be these sermons go way way back. היו נוהגים כך, hayu
nohagim kach, ושם היו נקבצים, vesham hayu nikpatzin,
it's actually true, some of the מדרשים Midrashim really, you know, are
understood to be like early sermons anyway. ושם היו נקבצים כל העם
לשמוע, vesham hayu nikpatzin kol ha'am lishmoa,
and everybody would gather. So it was an ideally thing, it wasn't
a weekly thing, it was a daily thing... Right. Well the well
the no well no Rashi is saying this about the יהא שמיה
רבא. Yehei Shmei Rabba. Oh yeah, the קדיש, Kaddish, right, not the
קדושה דסידרא. Kedusha DeSidra. לפי שאינו יום של מלאכה ויש כאן תורה
וקידוש השם. Lefi she'eino yom shel melacha veyeish kan Torah vekiddush Hashem.
Everybody's learning תורה Torah and everybody's saying יהא שמיה רבא. Yehei Shmei
Rabba. So the combination of a minim
of a type of a universal תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and a
universal קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem that brings everybody together and that allow
gives access to everyone, that is at least the minimum amount that
keeps the world going.
But he says they actually had a full Kaddish text, right?
Or it could just mean... Yeah, you don't know exactly whether it
was the exact same text, but clearly the structure was there. Okay,
so now the Gemara continues, שנאמר, shene'emar, ארץ עפתה כמו אפל, eretz
afaisa kmo ofel, the land was like in shrouded in darkness, כמו
אפל צלמות kmo ofel tzalmaves and great darkness, ולא סדרים, velo sedarim,
without order. היש סדרים? Hayesh sedarim? If there is these orders, the
order of קדושה Kedusha and the order of קדיש. Kaddish. So then
תופיע מאופל tofei'ah me-ofel you will be sort of saved you know
from the darkness. Okay.
Interesting choice of סדר Seder because
that because the סדר Seder is an order but
I don't know it's a fixed type of a thing I don't
know. Okay. ולא ירדה לברכה ונתמעט טעם פירות. v'lo yardah l'vrachah v'nitma'et
ta'am peirot. And also since the חורבן הבית, Churban Ha-Bayit, the rain,
the dew never came down, I mean for, yeah, the dew never
came down for blessing and
and there was no, the fruit, the taste of the fruit was
lacking. So I just have to share with you this, in keeping
in the theme of everything we've been learning and now talking about
the loss of the taste of the fruit. So נחום סרנא עליו
השלום, Nachum Sarna alav ha-shalom, you know that one, I told you
that one. נחום סרנא Nachum Sarna liked to tell this joke. He
said, you know, he said, why is it that all these Jewish
foods start with the letter like K, like קיכל kichal and קניידל
knaidel and קוגל? kugel? So he said because, you know, in the
time of the בית המקדש, Beit Ha-Mikdash, we had the most amazing
foods in the world. You know, they tasted like גן עדן. Gan
Eden. They were called things like
איכל, ichal, ניידל, naidel, אוגל. ugal. He says now it's just כאיכל,
ke-ichal, כניידל, ke-naidel, כקוגל. ke-kugel. Okay, badum-dum. Okay, that was. Anyway, badum-dum.
All right, anyway, so that was like a really bad joke.
You liked that?
No, because those foods are so bad.
I can't disagree with his Sephardic rap.
All right,
so now,
okay. Okay, תניא. Tanya. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר. Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar omer. טהרה בטלה טעם וריח. Taharah batlah ta'am v'rei'ach. The loss
of טהרה Taharah caused the cessation of the taste and the smell
of fruit. רש״י Rashi has a nice explanation for this. If you
look at רש״י, Rashi, ביטלה טעם, bitlah ta'am, like again, it's eight
lines from the bottom of the first column. הפירות וריחן שמתוך שהיו
טהורין ונוהגין בטהרה הקדוש ברוך הוא מטהר פירותיהם מריח רע ומטעם רע.
ha-peirot v'reichan she-mitoch she-hayu tehorin v'nohagin b'taharah Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu metaher peiroteihem
me-rei'ach ra u-mi-ta'am ra. He cleansed them, the metaphysical purity led to
a purity of smell and a purity of taste.
Okay. מעשר ביטלו שומן דגן. Ma'aser bitlu shuman dagan. And lack of
giving מעשר Ma'aser caused the fatness, the you know, of the of
the grain to be ceased. Because also the מעשר Ma'aser is called
כל חלב דגן ותירוש ויצהר. kol chelev dagan v'tirosh v'yitzhar. So it's
called the fatness is what we give. That's the you mean you
give from the best to God. So if you're not giving it,
that causes the fatness to get to be ceased.
And even literally if you're trying to keep more for yourself, מידה
כנגד מידה. middah k'neged middah.
That's what I mean. That's what I mean. Instead of giving the
fatness to God, exactly. By you giving it, yeah exactly. רב הונא
אשכח תמרתא דחינוניתא. Rav Huna ashkach tamarta d'chinunita. He found this
fatty, delicious, you know very sweet
date. Apparently רש״י Rashi says it's a particular species that's extremely fatty
and sweet, juicy I would say I guess. שקלה כרכה בסודריה. shaklah
karchah b'sudrei. He took it, he wrapped it in his handkerchief, you
know, and he wanted to give it as we'll see to his
son. אתא רבה בריה. Ata Rabbah breih. Rabbah his son came. אמר
ליה. Amar lei. And Rabbah said... מורחינא ריחא דחינוניתא. murchina reicha d'chinunita.
So Rabbah said I guess this date was in his pocket and
Rabbah his son said oh my god I smell the smell of
this amazing date. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him
בני טהרה יש בך. Bni, taharah yesh becha. You must have a
special purity that you at least have that sense to be able
that sense to the ability as we saw טהרה taharah leads to
you know the the the smell and the taste. So you're able
to have that smell so you must have some special purity to
be able to smell that smell. יהבה ניהליה. Yahavah nihalei. He gave
it to him. אדהכי אתא אבא בריה. Ad'hachi ata Abba breih. So
then Abba the son of of Rabbah came. So this was this
was right. So רב הונא's Rav Huna grandson. שקליה רבה ויהביה ליה.
Shaklei Rabbah v'yahvei lei. So Rabbah took it and gave it to
his son. אמר ליה. Amar lei. So רב הונא Rav Huna said
to רבה, Rabbah, בני שמחתני לבי. Bni, simachtani libi. You made my
heart rejoice that you were able to you know smell this thing,
it means that you have special purity of soul. אבל הקהית את
שיני. aval hikhita et shinai. You blunted my teeth. You also hurt
me because now you showed that you'd rather than making me happy
by taking what I've given you, you wanted you'd rather give it
to your son. היינו דאמרי אינשי. Hainu d'amrei inshi. That's what people
say. רחמי דאבא אבני. Rachamei d'abba a-vnei. The love of a father
is for his son. אבל רחמי דבני אבני דהוו ליה. aval rachamei
d'vnei a-vnei d'havu lei. But then the son's feelings and you know
affection and love is not always paid back to the father,
but it's for his sons. Okay so parents always love their children
you know not always, it's more I know I know that is
funny but it's yeah.
That's kind of sad that he gave it to him and then
he gave it to his son.
Oh that's a nice response,
God אבינו שבשמים Avinu She-ba-shamayim gave it to him, that's a nice
response. But anyway but you know but it is the idea that
the sort of natural, I'm not saying this is always the time
I mean sadly there are bad parents out there, but the natural
sense that you know parents give more and feel more for their
children which is not always you know which is not always sort
of reciprocated. So now we actually have a sad little end to
that maybe in the theme of everything going downhill, so רבא. Rava.
רב אחא בר יעקב *Rav Aha bar Yaakov* איסתיביה *istivaye* רב יעקב
בר ברתיה *Rav Yaakov bar barte* בר ברתיה *bar bartei*, רב אחא
בר יעקב *Rav Aha bar Yaakov* raised רב יעקב *Rav Yaakov*, his
grandson, his daughter's son. כדגדל *kidegadal*, when רב יעקב *Rav Yaakov* grew
up, אמר ליה amar leh *amar lei*, so then רב אחא *Rav
Aha* who's spent his, you know, all these years raising him, said
to him, אשקין מיא *ashkin maya*. So, you know, could you please
pour me a glass of water? אמר ליה *amar lei*, לאו אבונא
את *lav avuna at*. No, I'm not your son, I don't owe
you any honor. So which was pretty amazing. והיינו דאמרי אינשי *vehainu
d'amri inshi*, that's what people say, רבי Rebbe רבי Rebbe ורבי ליה
*rabi rabi verabi lei*, raise and raise the kids, ובסוף אמר בר
ברתך אנא *ubesof amar bar bartekh ana*, I'm actually your daughter's son
and I'm not your son and therefore I don't owe you honor,
which is like pretty heavy. Wow, so just keeping in the theme
about how things have gone to pot. Okay, so now the last
משנה Mishna, *mishna*. בפולמוס של אספסיינוס *bepulmus shel aspasyanus*, in the בפולמוס
*pulmus*, like polemic, but means like the wars, the wars of Vespasian,
I believe is אספסיינוס *aspasyanus*. So גזרו על עטרות חתנים atarot chatanim
*gazru al atrot hatanim*, they made a גזירה *gezeira*. So now as
opposed to like the whole world going to pot, I mean, this
is actually, this is a slightly different note, this is in response
to the חורבן הבית *hurban habayit*, things that we are going to
do to limit our joy, okay, to reflect the idea about how
we are, you know, have been impacted by the loss of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *beit hamikdash*. So this is like זכר לחורבן
*zecher l'hurban*. It's actually interesting, רב *Rav* Soloveitchik talked, you know, emphasized
that there's a difference between זכר למקדש *zecher l'mikdash* and זכר לחורבן
*zecher l'hurban*. We do certain things like זכר למקדש *zecher l'mikdash*, you
know, taking the לולב *lulav* all seven days. Okay, but that's to
remember what the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash. *beit hamikdash* was like when
it was up and running, you know, the, you know, the, whereas
this is זכר לחורבן *zecher l'hurban* to remember the act, the fact
that it is בחורבנו *behurbano*. Interesting also in the תוספתא *tosefta* at
the end of סוטה *Sotah*. By the way, if you haven't had
enough אגדתא *agadata* on this last פרק *perek*, you can go read
the תוספתא *tosefta* and you'll see even more אגדתא *agadata* related to
everything we've been dealing with. But in the last אגדתא *agadata* it
deals with the famous story about after the חורבן הבית *hurban habayit*,
you know, who was it, somebody ran into these people who basically
said that well we're, you know, we don't want to drink wine
and eat any meat now that there's no בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash,
*beit hamikdash*. Yeah, and then he said, well then you shouldn't eat
grain because we would also bring grain קרבנות *korbanot*, and you shouldn't
have fruit and you shouldn't have whatever and like אין גוזרין גזירה
על הציבור אלא אם כן רוב הציבור יכולים לעמוד בה *ein gozrin
gezeira al hatzibur ela im ken rov hatzibur yakholim laamod bah*. Our
response has to be a measured response. So we can't not respond
and we can't be, you know, overly indulge, we have to move
forward, we have to have a measured response. Okay, so what did
the גזירה *gezeira* did they make? על עטרות חתנים *al atrot hatanim*,
so not to have the crowns that grooms would wear. ועל האירוס
*veal hairus*, we'll see what אירוס *irus* is, it's sort of apparently
some drums. Okay. בפולמוס של טיטוס *bepulmus shel titus*, and in the
wars of Titus, so which is again getting closer to the actual
destruction, I guess Vespasian left and sent Titus in his place. גזרו
על עטרות כלות *gazru al atrot kalot*, so the crowns that the
brides would wear. ושלא ילמד אדם את בנו יוונית *veshelo yilamed adam
et beno yevanit*, and that a person should not teach his son
Greek. Okay, we'll see what that's about. בפולמוס האחרון *bepulmus haaharon*, in
the last battle, when it now could mean the act of the
חורבן הבית *hurban habayit*, which again would just be Titus, so some
want to say actually it might be referring to the, to the,
you know, in the times of בר כוכבא *Bar Kokhba*, right, exactly,
the Great Revolt, 135 or something like that. Yeah, exactly. So גזרו
שלא תצא כלה באפיריון gazru she-lo seitzei kallah be-apiryon, בתוך
העיר *gazru shelo tetze kala baapiryon betokh hair*, a bride should not
go out in her wedding in some type of like a carriage,
בתוך העיר
*betokh hair*, into the city. ורבותינו התירו *veraboteinu hitiru*, and the Rabbis
allowed. Actually in כתובות *Ketubot* one way you know that it was
a first wedding for a woman was that she was going out,
everybody saw her going out in this chariot etc. התירו שתצא כלה
kallah, באפיריון בתוך העיר *hitiru shetetze kala baapiryon betokh hair*. משמת רבי
Mishemess Rebbe, מאיר
*mishemmet rabi meir*, now we switch, so that's like גזירות *gezeirot* to
respond to חורבן הבית *hurban habayit*. Okay, first it spoke because of
the חורבן הבית *hurban habayit* the world's gone to pot and now
how do we demonstrate our mourning over חורבן הבית *hurban habayit*. Now
we're back to everything that we've lost from previous generations. משמת רבי
Mishemess Rebbe, מאיר *mishemmet rabi meir*, when רבי Rebbi מאיר *rabi meir*
died, בטלו מושלי משלים *batlu moshlei meshalim*, those that would sort of
give, you know, parables, he was very good at giving parables. משמת
בן עזאי בטלו השקדנים mishemet Ben Azzai batlu hashakdanim, *mishemmet ben azai
batlu hashaqdanim*, when בן עזאי *ben azai* died, those that would sort
of be, you know, diligent, like you know, to give all, you
know, to in their תורה Torah *torah* study, unceasing diligence in their
תורה Torah *torah* study. משמת בן זומא בטלו הדרשנים mishemet Ben Zoma
batlu hadarshanim, *mishemmet ben zoma batlu hadarshanim*, when בן זומא *ben zoma*
died, people that could give דרשות *drashot*, although דרשות *drashot* here probably
means less of אגדתא *agadata* and more רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it
means interpreting פסוקים Psukim *psukim* like when you know עד שדרשה בן
זומא *ad she-darsha ben zoma*, לא זכיתי שתאמר יציאת מצרים בלילות עד
שדרשה בן זומא *lo zakhiti she-teamer yetziat mitzrayim baleilot ad she-darsha ben
zoma*. So learning things from פסוקים pesukim, *psukim*. משמת רבי mishemet Rebbe,
עקיבא בטל כבוד התורה Batal Kevod HaTorah, *mishemmet rabi akiva batel kvod
hatorah*, the honor of תורה Torah *torah*, because what רבי עקיבא *rabi
akiva* was able to do with his, you know, hermeneutics was really
the tremendous honor of the תורה Torah *torah* from every tiny little
extra letter. משמת mishemet רבי חנינא בן דוסא *mishemmet rabi hanina ben
dosa*, and when רבי חנינא בן דוסא *rabi hanina ben dosa* died,
בטלו אנשי מעשה *batlu anshei maaseh*, people of wonder who do wonders,
because there are stories about רבי חנינא בן דוסא *rabi hanina ben
dosa*, you know, that he was like a wonder, a miracle doer
or something, there, you know, and all these wonders occurred when he,
you know, when he would do
things. whatever around him.
Where are we?
בטלו אנשי מעשה. משמת רבי יוסי Mishemess Rabbi Yosi when רבי יוסי
הקטנתא Rabbi Yosi HaKatanta when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi the small died,
פסקו החסידים, Pasqu HaChasidim, the truly righteous ones died or the pious
ones. Thank you. ולמה נקרא שמו קטנתא, V'lamah Nikra Shemo Katanta, why
was he called small? שהיה קטנתא של חסידים, Shehayah Katanta Shel Chasidim,
because he was even the smallest of the pious, and that's why
when he died, there was no longer any pious around.
משמת רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, Mishemess Rabbi Yochanan Ben Zakkai, when יוחנן
בן זכאי Yochanan Ben Zakkai died, בטל זיו החכמה, Batal Ziv HaChokhmah,
the shining of wisdom went out. So רש״י Rashi says that means,
רש״י Rashi gives sort of situates everybody else in other stories about
them, but here רש״י Rashi says לא ידענא מאי היא, Lo Yadana
Mai Hi, I don't know exactly what the connection is. משמת רבן
גמליאל הזקן, Mishemess Rabban Gamliel HaZaken, when רבן גמליאל הזקן Rabban Gamliel
HaZaken died, בטל כבוד התורה, the honor of תורה torah, died because
רבן גמליאל הזקן Rabban Gamliel HaZaken was,
because רש״י Rashi says that the גמרא Gemara in מגילה Megillah says
that after he died, people got much less healthy. So therefore, if
people are less healthy, they're learning, they're not learning תורה torah. as
much. ומתה טהרה ופרישות, Umesah Taharah U'Perishus, and it was the end
of purity and of asceticism. משמת רבי ישמעאל בן פאבי, Mishemess Rabbi
Yishmael Ben Pabi, when רבי ישמעאל בן פאבי Rabbi Yishmael Ben Pabi
died, who was very wealthy and he supported כהנים, Kohanim, בטלה זיו
הכהונה, Batlah Ziv HaKehunah, the glowing of כהונה Kehunah departed. משמת רבי,
when רבי died, which is interesting because we always think that רבי
was the final editor of the משנה, Mishna okay,
so משמת רבי, בטלה ענוה ויראת חטא. mishemet Rebbe batlah anavah v'yirat
chet, So the
modesty and true fear of sin departed. Now, that's a pretty depressing
way to end
the מסכת. Masechet. I mean, you can, we'll see how the גמרא
Gemara ends it, but you know, you hope a משנה Mishna would
end it in a more, the last משנה Mishna of a מסכת
Masechet usually ends on an up note, and you'll see right here
there's in brackets, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, because there actually is a
question whether the next line is from the משנה Mishna. or not.
And in a lot of גרסאות, Girsaos, they have the next line
from the משנה. Mishna. So let's read the next line and then
I'll tell you how some have the very last line of the
משנה. Mishna. So anyway, the way we have it, which was תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, but some have this as part of the משנה.
Mishna. רבי פנחס בן יאיר אומר משחרב בית המקדש בושו חברים, Rabbi
Pinchas Ben Yair Omer Mishecharav Beis HaMikdash Boshu Chaverim, the חברים, Chaverim,
right, those who were like the colleagues of the who would eat
things with טהרה, Taharah, you know, became embarrassed, ובני חורין, U'Vnei Chorin,
and those who are, what's בני חורין? Bnei Chorin? We normally talk
about on פסח Pesach about acting reclining as a way of בני
חורין, Bnei Chorin, but you look at רש״י, Rashi, this always bothered
me, and if you look at רש״י Rashi about eight lines from
the bottom in the left-hand column, מיוחסים, Meyuchasim, people of good lineage,
like people of status. Because you always like, since when is it
that a way of free people is to recline and to drink
wine? Like, I don't know, that's what freedom is about? So I
always assumed it meant that because, well, maybe if being free in
a, as a Roman citizen, you know, being a citizen normally came
was associated with status, although logically it's not necessarily the same. Anyway,
here clearly בני חורין Bnei Chorin just is not the opposite of
being a slave. בני חורין Bnei Chorin specifically means somebody of status.
Okay, ובני חורין, U'Vnei Chorin, so they were all like shamed and
embarrassed, וכפפו ראשם, VeChafu Rosham, they're sort of, their, you know, their
heads were
shrouded,
ונדלדלו אנשי מעשה, VeNidaldelu Anshei Maaseh, people of deeds were, you know,
decreased, וגברו בעלי זרוע, VeGavru Baalei Zeroah, people of violence or of,
you know, having their way by force, you know, were supreme, ובעלי
לשון, U'Baalei Lashon, and people that would, you know, of the tongue
that would use their obviously would lie and cheat, etc., and spread
ill repute. ואין דורש ואין מבקש, VeEin Doreish VeEin Mevakesh, there is
none to seek out and there is none to ask. What does
that mean? I mean, it's a nice alliteration. But רש״י Rashi says,
אין דורש לישראל, Ein Doreish L'Yisroel,
meaning nobody is concerned about people's well-being. Everybody's about getting ahead on
their own. And therefore nobody is to לבקש עליהם רחמים Levakesh Aleihem
Rachamim for them from God. ואין שואל, VeEin Shoel, and there's none
to ask to help us. על מי לנו להשען על אבינו שבשמים,
Al Mi Lanu Lehishayen Al Avinu Shebashamayim, who do we have to
rely on?
We only have our God in heaven. רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר מיום
שחרב בית המקדש, Rabbi Eliezer HaGadol Omer Miyom Shecharav Beis HaMikdash, from
the time that the בית המקדש was destroyed,
שרו חכימיא למהוי כספריא, Sharu Chakimaya Lemahavei K'Safraya, the sages became like
the חדר Cheder teachers, like the people who would just teach in
a פסוקים to the kids in school. וספריא כחזניא, V'Safraya K'Chazzanaya, and
the חדר Cheder teachers became like the חזנים Chazzanim in the שול.
Shul. וחזניא כעמא דארעא, V'Chazzanaya K'Amma D'Ara, and the חזנים Chazzanim became
like the עם הארץ. Am HaAretz. Everybody went down a level. ועמא
דארעא, V'Amma D'Ara, so what happened to the עם הארץ? Am HaAretz?
אזלא ודלדלה, Azla VeDildela, or has some version ונבלה, V'Navla, they kept
on going and getting worse and worse, going more and more to
pot. ואין שואל ואין מבקש, VeEin Shoel VeEin Mevakesh, there's none to
ask after people's well-being, you know, who cares about the well-being or
to ask for us from God. על מי לנו להשען אבינו שבשמים,
Al Mi Lanu Lehishayen Avinu Shebashamayim, in the time our our our
father in heaven.
So if it ends there, and some actually have it ending there,
that's not so bad. I mean, things are going to pot, but
at least it does end with a hope of like, well, God
is always there to protect us. Okay, now there are more, but
some people do have that in their גירסא Girsa of the משנה.
Mishna. of the משנה. Now, and some end the line because we
mentioned פנחס בן יאיר Pinchas ben Yair before. The גמרא Gemara does
not elaborate on this, so it's doubtful the גמרא Gemara had the
line. It's not printed in our גמרא. Gemara. But some משניות Mishnayot
have the following line from רב פנחס בן יאיר Rav Pinchas ben
Yair who we quoted earlier, which is a famous line. רב פנחס
בן יאיר אומר זריזות מביאה לידי נקיות נקיות מביאה לידי טהרה טהרה
מביאה לידי פרישות פרישות מביאה לידי קדושה קדושה מביאה לידי ענווה ענווה
מביאה לידי יראת חטא יראת חטא מביאה לידי חסידות חסידות מביאה לידי
רוח הקודש רוח הקודש מביאה לידי תחיית המתים ותחיית המתים בו יבוא
יבוא בא על ידי אליהו זכור
לטוב. Rav Pinchas ben Yair omer: Zerizut mevia lidei nekiut, nekiut mevia
lidei tahara, tahara mevia lidei perishut, perishut mevia lidei kedusha, kedusha mevia
lidei anava, anava mevia lidei yirat chet, yirat chet mevia lidei chasidut,
chasidut mevia lidei ruach hakodesh, ruach hakodesh mevia lidei techiyat hametim, u’techiyat
hametim bo yavo yavo ba al yedei Eliyahu zachur latov. So that's
a nicer way to end a מסכת. masechet. So everything might be
going to pot, but it's talking about sort of reversing it and
it's talking about here ways you can take small little incremental steps
to actually raise your level of righteousness, carefulness with מצוות, mitzvot, getting
closer to God even in this world. There's a ladder you can
go up and eventually we can reverse this process and משיח Mashiach
can come. So I think that's like such a powerful and necessary
way to end it, right, which is sad that it's not in
our גרסה, girsa, yeah.
That reminds me of that section in עבודה זרה Avoda Zara that's
from... turned into... מסילת ישרים. Mesillat Yesharim.
Well no, that is, that is exactly that statement serves as the
structure for the רמח"ל's Ramchal מסילת ישרים. Mesillat Yesharim. But anyway, it's
a nicer way to end a... much nicer way. Okay, now I
realize we have 20 minutes so we gotta move. Okay, but that
would be a nice way to end it. Okay, now, back to
the גמרא. Gemara. So this is maybe a ברייתא, braita, maybe who
knows. Anyway, moving on. בעקבתא דמשיחא, Be’ikvata d’Meshicha, you ever hear the
phrase עקבתא דמשיחא? ikvata d’Meshicha? Right, that comes here because, okay, the
footsteps of משיח. Mashiach. In the period living up to משיח, Mashiach,
and this maybe also is a way of putting a positive spin.
Things have really gone to pot, but ultimately, the worse things get,
that's the echoes or whatever, the foreshadowing of the beginning of משיח,
Mashiach, the footsteps of משיח. Mashiach. Okay, so there's a joke like
that which is somebody who's a real follower of רב קוק Rav
Kook his whole life and he spreads the תורה of about religious
Zionism. Anyway, when he dies, he goes to גיהנום. Gehennom. So he
goes to גיהנום, Gehennom, so he calls out, he says, he says,
הרב קוק, HaRav Kook, he says, הרב, HaRav, all my life I've
devoted to you, I followed your teachings, he says, what am I
doing here in גיהנום? Gehennom? He says, ah, עקבתא דגן עדן. ikvata
d’Gan Eden.
So, all right. So,
בעקבתא דמשיחא, Be’ikvata d’Meshicha, in the footsteps of משיח, Mashiach, חוצפא יסגא,
chutzpa yasga, temerity, חוצפה chutzpa will increase. ויוקר יאמיר, veyoker yaamir, and
honor will be perverted. הגפן תתן פריה, Hagefen titein pirya, even if
though the vine is giving its grape, והיין ביוקר, vehayayin beyoker, but
wine is very expensive because everybody is just running after hedonistic pleasures.
ומלכות תהפך למינות, U’malchut tahafech leminut, the kingdom will turn to מינות.
minut. Now what is מינות? minut? Heresy. That's bizarre. Why should we
care about the non-Jewish government being heretical? But if you look at
רש"י Rashi. in the right-hand column, at least mine, I don't know
if yours has it,
but the very far right-hand column it has this thing that was
edited out of רש"י. Rashi So רש"י says, המלכות השולטת על רוב
העולם תהיה למינות נהפכים אחר טעות שלו or של ישו ותלמידיו, נקראו
מינים. nikrau Minim. So therefore basically it means the Roman government is
going to turn into a Christian government, right, become the Holy Roman
Empire.
So תהפך למינות tahafech leminut ואין תוכחה ve’ein tochecha or whatever, nobody
will... there's no remonstrating or whatever giving תוכחה tochecha because everybody is
equally sinning and you'll say how can you give
me מוסר, mussar, how about your deeds? בית ועד יהיה לזנות, Beit
va’ad yihiyeh liznut, the house of gathering which is used for תורה
which will become a place of
prostitution. והגליל יחרב והגבלן יישום, Vehagalil yecherav vehagavlan yaishom, and this place
called
הגבלן hagavlan will become desolate. ואנשי הגבול יסובבו מעיר לעיר ולא יחוננו,
Ve’anshei hagvul yesovevu me’ir le’ir velo yechonenu, and they won't find any
peace. וחכמת סופרים תסרח ויראי חטא ימאסו והאמת תהא נעדרת, Ve’chochmat sofrim
tisrach veyirei chet yimasu ve’ha’emet tehei ne’ederet, truth will be lacking, will
be
rare. נערים פני זקנים ילבינו זקנים יעמדו מפני קטנים, Ne’arim pnei zekenim
yalbinu zekenim yaamdu mipnei ktanim, elders will be expected to stand in
front of the
youth. Okay. בן מנבל אב בת קמה באמה כלה בחמותה אויבי איש
אנשי ביתו, Ben menavel av bat kama be’ima kala bachamota oivei ish
anshei beito, a person's enemies will be within his very household. Makes
you almost think about like in Russia, right, when you had to
be people would be like informers in the very house. פני הדור
כפני הכלב, Pnei hador k’pnei hakelev, the face of the generation looks
like the face of the dog. the face of the generation looks
like the face of dogs. Either it means that they're very cruel
or uncaring. I don't know, dogs sometimes are
very happy to see
you. Anyway, הבן אינו מתבייש habein eino mitbayes מאביו me'aviv a son
is not embarrassed from his father of acting in certain ways. ועל
מה יש לנו
להישען ve'al mah yesh lanu lehisha'en who do we have to support
to rely on? על אבינו שבשמים al avinu shebashamayim only our Father
in heaven. אמר רב amar Rav לא שנו אלא של מלח וגופרית.
lo shanu ela shel melach vegofrit. Now back to Halacha. Okay, back
to the first part of the Mishnah about the עטרות חתנים about
the crowns of grooms that we don't have from the time of
the Vespasian wars. So that's only those crowns made out of salt
and sulfur, apparently some type of a rock they would make it
out of. אבל של הדס ושל ורד aval shel hadas veshel vered
which seems like a nicer crown to me, one of myrtle and
rose, מותר mutar it's permissible. שמואל אמר אף של הדס ושל ורד
אסור Shmuel amar af shel hadas veshel vered asur even that's forbidden.
של קנים ושל חילת מותר shel kanim veshel chilat mutar but if
you make it out of reeds and some type of seaweed that's
permissible. לוי אמר אף של קנים ושל חילת אסור Levi amar af
shel kanim veshel chilat asur even that's forbidden. וכן תני לוי במתניתא
vechen tani Levi bematnita that's what he taught in the Baraita, אף
של קנים ושל חילת אסור af shel kanim veshel chilat asur even
one of reeds is forbidden. ועל אירוס ve'al irus what's an irus?
מאי אירוס? mai irus? אמר רב אלעזר amar Rav Elazar טבלא דחד
פומא tavla dechad puma some type of a
tableau of one mouth. So Rashi says it means like a clapper
on a bell, maybe it means like a gong or something. Because
now what we're really going to do is compare it to or
explain it as a type of a drum. רבה בר רב הונא
עבד ליה לבריה תנבורא Rabbah bar Rav Huna avad leh livreih tanbura
tanbur, right, isn't that what we call tambourine or whatever? Anyway, but
Rashi sounds like it's more like a drum and he actually describes
how you would make a drum. Interesting Rashi if you want to
look at it, we don't have time for it today. אתא אבוה
תבריה ata avuh tavreih his father came and he broke it. אמר
ליה נחלף בטבלא דחד פומא nichlaf betavla dechad puma no, that will
get confused with this other thing which is forbidden, which is again
maybe some type of a gong or something. So
זיל עביד ליה אפומא דחצבא zil avid leh apuma dechatztzava if you're
going to make a drum, make it on the mouth of a
pot,
או אפומא דקפיזא o apuma dekafiza or some other type of a
household container so that it does not get confused with one of
these musical instruments which is actually forbidden. Okay, ובפולמוס של טיטוס גזרו
על עטרות כלות uvafolmos shel Titus gazru al atarot kallot then when
Titus's wars came, even the brides couldn't wear crowns. So מאי עטרות
כלות mai atarot kallot what are these? אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan עיר
של זהב ir shel zahav some type of a tiara that looked
out of gold that had etched like it looked like the city
or Yerushalayim. תניא נמי הכי tanya nami hachi איזו הן עטרות כלות
eizu hen atarot kallot what's an atarot kallot? עיר של זהב. ir
shel zahav. אבל עושה היא כיפה של מילת aval oseih hi kippah
shel milat but what you can do is you can make some
type of a head covering of like silk. I think milat is
silk. תנא אף על חופת חתנים גזרו tana af al chuppat chatanim
gazru so even said that you can't have a fancy chuppah. מאי
חופת חתנים mai chuppat chatanim what was a chuppah? זהורית מזהבת zehorit
mezuhevet so this means like some type of a shining with gold.
So Rashi says it means like a tallis made
out
of crimson which had like a gold trim and they would use
sort of that to make a chuppah. So that was a type
of a chuppah that was not appropriate. But other types of chuppah
you could have. If you look at Rashi again, 12 lines up
from the bottom on the right hand column: זהורית מזהבת zehorit mezuhevet
טלית צבוע שני tallit tzavu'a shani ובוקעים בו פסי זהב uvoke'im bo
pasei zahav they would have like gold
whatever ornaments on it, עד שמעמידים אותו כמין כיפה ad shema'amidin oto
kemin kippah and they would basically make like a tent out of
it or something. אבל עושה aval oseih so then the Gemara says
תניא נמי הכי tanya nami hachi we taught similarly,
אלו הן חופת חתנים elu hen chuppat chatanim fine, תניא נמי הכי
אלו הן חופת חתנים זהורית מזהבת tanya nami hachi elu hen chuppat
chatanim zehorit mezuhevet אבל עושה פפירית aval oseih papirit you can make
a papirit, ותולה בה כל מה שירצה vetoleh bah kol mah sheyirtzeh
and you can suspend on it any types of ornaments that you
want. So what's a papirit that's different? So Rashi says כמין כיפה
של מעגלי עץ kemin kippah shel ma'aglei etz כמו שאנו עושים kemo
she'anu osim ותולין בה צניפים ורדידי זהב vetolin bah tznifim urdidei zahav
כמו שאנו עושים. kemo she'anu osim. It's very interesting describing what his
chuppah looks like. I don't know exactly what he means by ma'aglei
etz. Does it mean like arches of wood? What do you think
ma'aglei etz means? Some type of wooden arches that they would use
for the chuppah so they wouldn't have the poles with it would
be more like a dome I guess.
Yeah, maybe or when a chuppah tallis come in after yichud and
people come and they've got some arch around it or something.
Okay fine maybe or they're self-you know.
Okay got it. ושלא ילמד בנו יוונית veshelo yilamed bno yevanit not
to teach your son Greek. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan כשצרו keshetzaru another
famous story, here's another Gemara, I think also in Josephus if I'm
not mistaken. כשצרו מלכי בית חשמונאי זה על זה keshetzaru malchei beit
Chashmonai zeh al zeh oh Chanukah
time. When the beit Chashmonai were at war when it was not
against the Seleucids, a few generations later when they were warring amongst
themselves.
היה הורקנוס מבחוץ ואריסטובלוס מבפנים hayah Hurkanos mibachutz ve'Aristoblos mibifnim Hyrcanus was
on the outside of Yerushalayim and he had these Roman troops with
him and Aristobulus was on the inside. ובכל יום ויום היו משלשלין
דינרין בקופה uvechol yom vayom hayu meshalshelin dinarin bekuppah they would lower
down dinars in a basket to those outside, ומעלין להם תמידין uma'alin
lahem temidin and those outside would put in these sheep for... bring
as תמידים temidim sacrifices because everybody still cared about the עבודה avodah
in the בית המקדש. היה שם זקן אחד שהיה מכיר בחכמה יוונית,
Hayah sham zaken echad she-hayah makir be-chochmah Yevanis, there was a certain
elder person elderly
person on the inside of the walls who knew חכמה יוונית, chochmah
Yevanis, which is apparently a secret way of signaling to people. לעז
להם בחכמה יוונית, La'az lahem be-chochmah Yevanis, he whispered to them in
his in this Greek wisdom, he somehow signaled to them, ואמר להם,
ve-amar lahem, and he indicated to them, כל זמן שעוסקים בעבודה, kol
zman she-oskim be-avodah, as long as they are doing the עבודה avodah
in the בית המקדש, אין נמסרים בידכם, ein nim-sarim be-yed-chem, that's keeping
them protected and they won't be given over. ולמחר שילשלו דינרים בקופה,
U-le-machar shil-shelu dinarim be-kuppah, so what happened the next day when they
lowered down the dinariums in the in the basket? והעלו להם חזיר,
Ve-he'alu lahem chazir, rather than putting in a sheep they put in
a pig. כיון שהגיע לחצי חומה, Keivan she-higia le-chatzi chomah, when it
got halfway up the wall, נעץ צפורניו, na'atz tzipornav, it put its
claws into the wall, ונזדעזעה ארץ ישראל ארבע מאות פרסה, ve-niz-da-za-ah Eretz
Yisrael arba meos parsah, and that the whole land of Israel shook,
you know, because of like the חילול השם chillul Hashem that was
being done. אותה שעה אמרו, Osah sha'ah amru, at that moment they
said, ארור אדם שיגדל חזירים, arur adam she-yigadel chazirim, cursed is the
person
who raises pigs, וארור אדם שילמד לבנו חכמה יוונית, ve-arur adam she-yelamed
li-vno chochmah Yevanis, cursed is the person who teaches his son Greek
wisdom. ובאותה שנה שנינו, U-ve-osah shanah shaninu, and for and that year
we taught, because when they were being besieged, מביאין העומר מגגות צריפין,
mavi'in ha-omer mi-gagots tzerifin, there was a time
they had to bring the עומר omer from like stored grain or
this place גגות צריפין, Gagots Tzerifin, ושתי הלחם מבקעת עין סוכר, ve-shtei
ha-lechem mi-bik-as Ein Socher, and the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem from some
this place called עין סוכר, Ein Socher, even
though normally you're supposed to bring these things from places near ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. Here they had to import it from far away because they
were besieged and because also the troops on the outside had burned
down all of the crops around ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, איני, eini, is
this really true? ואמר רב, Ve-amar Rav, that you can't teach Greek?
ואמר רב בארץ ישראל, Ve-amar Rav be-Eretz Yisrael, if you're in Israel,
רבי says it, לשון סורסי למה, leshon Sursi lamah, why should you
speak סורסי, Sursi, which is some type of a vernacular? Don't speak
Aramaic. Aramaic. Okay, אלא או לשון הקודש, ella o leshon ha-kodesh, either
speak Hebrew, לשון הקודש, leshon ha-kodesh, not Hebrew, לשון הקודש, leshon ha-kodesh,
או לשון יוונית, o leshon Yevanis, or Greek. If you don't want
to speak in לשון הקודש, leshon ha-kodesh, we have a very, you
know, elevated language, cultured language to speak, which is Greek. Why would
you be speaking Aramaic? ואמר רב יוסף, Ve-amar Rav Yosef, בבבל, be-Bavel,
if you're living in בבל, Bavel, לשון ארמי למה, leshon Arami lamah,
why would you want to speak in Aramaic? Again maybe a different
version, סורסי Sursi and ארמית. Aramis. אלא או לשון הקודש, Ella o
leshon ha-kodesh, either either speak לשון הקודש, leshon ha-kodesh, או לשון פרסי,
o leshon Parsi, or speak the Persian tongue, which I don't know
what that was. Anyway, Farsi maybe? Farsi, I guess it's Farsi. Yeah.
Okay, so anyway, these are more elevated languages. Why would you want
to speak Aramaic? Which I guess they saw some type of a
corrupt or a lowly language. So anyway, you see that you could
speak Greek. לשון יוונית לחוד, Leshon Yevanis lachud, the language is one
thing, חכמה יוונית לחוד, chochmah Yevanis lachud, the wisdom is another thing.
So you so you can speak the Greek language, but you should
not be able to you should not learn חכמה יוונית, chochmah Yevanis,
which was used in this devious way. וחכמת יוונית מי אסיר, Ve-chochmas
Yevanis mi asir, is that really forbidden? ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Ve-amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel, משום רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, mi-shum Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel, מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, what's meant by the פסוק
pasuk עיני עוללה לנפשי מכל בנות עירי, eini olelah le-nafshi mi-kol benos
iri, my eyes are sort of you know are cry over whatever
despair over my soul from all of the daughters of my city?
אלף ילדים היו בבית אבא, Elef yeladim hayu be-veis abba, so Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says, my father had a thousand children. I don't
want to imagine it's a bit of an exaggeration. חמש מאות למדו
תורה וחמש מאות למדו חכמה יוונית, chamesh meos lamdu Torah ve-chamesh meos
lamdu chochmah Yevanis, 500 learned Torah and 500 learned חכמה יוונית, chochmah
Yevanis, so some excelled in some went to university and some went
to ישיבה. yeshiva. ולא נשתייר מהם אלא אני, Ve-lo nishtayer me-hem ella
ani, and I'm the only one who's left, כאן, kan, ובית אחי
אבא, u-veis achi abba, and the son of my father's brother, באסיא,
be-Asya, in Asia. Anyway, so you see that the whole family learned
or half the family learned חכמה יוונית. chochmah Yevanis. הגמרא Ha-gemara says,
no, שאני של בית רבן שמעון בן גמליאל דקרובים למלכות הוו. shani
shel beis Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel de-krovim le-malchus havu. No, no, no,
they were the נשיא nasi and they had to keep up good
relations with the Roman government, so they were allowed to learn חכמה
יוונית. chochmah Yevanis. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, מספר
קומי הרי זה מדרכי האמורי, mesaper komi harei ze mi-darchei ha-Emori, somebody
cuts his hair in this way which was a pagan way, so
some type of like a thing sticking out in the back, anyway,
that's Emorite practices. אבטולמוס בן ראובן התירו לו לספר קומי, Avtolmos ben
Reuven hiti-ru lo le-saper komi, but they allowed this person to do
this, שקרוב למלכות, she-karov le-malchus, because he had dealings with the government,
so he had to look a particular way. של בית רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל התירו להם חכמה יוונית, Shel beis Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
hiti-ru lahem chochmah Yevanis, they allowed them to study חכמה יוונית, chochmah
Yevanis, מפני שקרובים למלכות. mipnei she-krovim le-malchus. Okay, question is that based
on what Rabban Gamliel had to do? Well then I don't know
if he's doing that necessarily. Anyway, so a question about whether that's
based on פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, this isn't איסור דאורייתא, issur de-oraisa,
anyway, but this is just you know exactly what it's based on,
but we do definitely have a category of קרוב למלכות. karov le-malchus.
Alright, בפולמוס של אחרון, Be-polmos shel acharon, in the last wars, presumably
again the Bar Kochba, גזרו שלא תצא כלה באפיריון, she can't doesn't
go out in a chariot, the כלה, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, משום
צניעותא. mi-shum tzni-usa. Very funny, what do you mean מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? What's מאי טעמא mai ta'ama of all of this? To show
a certain sense of you know of what was lost as a
result of the wars. Anyway, but maybe there's a sense of showing
greater greater like you know we shouldn't the צניעות tznius here is
not how we sometimes sadly translate צניעות, tznius, which is all about
how much of your
body you're exposing,
but no, it means like a modest way of being, you know,
you don't flaunt a you know and draw attention to yourself overly
much, and maybe it... So that's, you know, there's, so that's a
more of an ethos that we want to embrace even more. משמת
רבן יוחנן בטלה חכמה. mishemet Rabban Yochanan batlah chachmah. תנו רבנן: tanu
rabbanan: משמת רבי אליעזר נגנז ספר תורה. mishemet Rabbi Eliezer nignaz sefer
torah. So it's like he would, now Rashi is very important because
Rabbi Eliezer was not a מחדש, micha-desh, you know, he didn't use
his own sort of creativity like Rabbi Akiva, who is the opposite
of Rabbi Eliezer. Rabbi Eliezer stored all of the Torah he received
from his rebbes. He said he never said anything he didn't receive
from his rebbes. So he's the repository of Torah, like a ספר
תורה sefer torah is static, right? So when he died, the ספר
תורה sefer torah was buried. But that's a very, a very powerful
image. משמת רבי יהושע בטלה עצה, mishemet Rabbi Yehoshua batlah etzah, you
know, sort of sage advice, ומחשבה, u-machshavah, and insight. משמת רבי עקיבא
בטלו זרועי תורה, mishemet Rabbi Akiva batlu zero'ei torah, the power of
תורה, ונסתתמו מעינות החכמה, v'nistatmu ma'ayanot hachachmah, and the wellsprings of wisdom.
משמת because he obviously was a big מחדש micha-desh and used his
intellect and creativity and so on. משמת רבי אלעזר בן עזריה בטלו
עטרות חכמה, mishemet Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah batlu atorot chachmah, the crowns
of wisdom because I think was he wealthy? Rashi says, yeah, anyway,
yeah, yeah, he was very wealthy. So the crowns, the glory of
wisdom, שעטרת חכמים עשרם, she-ateret hachamim oshram, because the crowns of חכמים
chachamim is their wealth. משמת רבי חנינא בן דוסא בטלו אנשי מעשה,
mishemet Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa batlu anshei ma'aseh, people of deeds, of
miraculous deeds. משמת אבא יוסי בן קטנותא בטלו חסידים, mishemet Abba Yosi
ben Katnuta batlu chasidim, the pious. ולמה נקרא שמו אבא יוסי בן
קטנותא? v'lamah nikra shemo Abba Yosi ben Katnuta? Why was he called
the son of the small one? שהיה מקטני חסידים, she-hayah mikatnei chasidim,
he was even one of the minor of the pious. משמת בן
עזאי בטלו השקדנים, the שקדנים shakdanim end, those who dedicated themselves completely
to the learning of תורה. משמת בן זומא בטלו הדרשנים, those that
would דרשן darshan from פסוקים, but again more like מדרש הלכה. midrash
halacha. משמת רבן גמליאל עלה גובאי, mishemet Rabban Gamliel alah gobai, when
Rabban Gamliel died, the, what, the locusts, ורבו צרות, v'rabu tzarot, and
the sufferings increased. משמת רבי, when Rebbe died, הוכפלו צרות, huchpalu tzarot,
the sufferings got doubled. משמת רבי בטלה ענוה ויראת חטא, Batlah Anavah
VeYiras Cheit. when Rebbe died, humility and fear of sin. אמר ליה
רב יוסף לתנא, amar lei Rav Yosef l'tanna, Rav Yosef said to
the תנא: tanna: לא תתני ענוה, lo titni anavah, don't say that
there's no more humility, דאיכא אנא, d'ika ana, I'm still around! You've
got to love that! The גמרא gemara thankfully ends on a little
note of humor. We needed that at the end. Anyway, but it's
important that humility is not denying who you are, you know? When
משה Moshe was ענו מכל אדם, anav mikol adam, it didn't mean
that he didn't know his own greatness; it meant how you hold
yourself, you know? Not a false modesty. Exactly. Anyway, but also besides
the little, besides finally the little humor break, I think it's also
nice because again it ends with a note that like, it's not
all terrible, like there is still some good left in the world.
אמר ליה רב נחמן לתנא, amar lei Rav Nachman l'tanna, similarly Rav
Nachman said to the תנא: tanna: לא תתני יראת חטא, lo titni
yirat chet, don't say there's no longer fear of sin, דאיכא אנא,
d'ika ana, I'm still, I'm still around. So again, a little humor
but a little sense, you know what, things are not completely lost.
Okay. הדרן עלך מסכת סוטה. hadran alach masechet sotah. So we should
just, so let's just go for it. Okay. הדרן עלך מסכת סוטה
ודעתן עלך מסכת סוטה דעתך עלן לא נתנשי מינך מסכת סוטה ולא
תתנשי מינן לא בעלמא הדין ולא בעלמא דאתי. hadran alach masechet sotah
v'da'atan alach masechet sotah da'atach alan lo nitnishi minach masechet sotah v'lo
titnishi minan lo b'alma hadein v'lo b'alma d'atei. הדרן עלך מסכת סוטה
ודעתן עלך מסכת סוטה דעתך עלן לא נתנשי מינך מסכת סוטה ולא
תתנשי מינן לא בעלמא הדין ולא בעלמא דאתי.
hadran alach masechet sotah v'da'atan alach masechet sotah da'atach alan lo nitnishi
minach masechet sotah v'lo titnishi
minan lo b'alma hadein v'lo b'alma d'atei. הדרן עלך מסכת סוטה ודעתן
עלך מסכת סוטה דעתך עלן לא נתנשי מינך מסכת סוטה ולא תתנשי
מינן לא בעלמא הדין ולא בעלמא דאתי. hadran alach masechet sotah v'da'atan
alach masechet sotah da'atach alan lo nitnishi minach masechet sotah v'lo titnishi
minan lo b'alma hadein v'lo b'alma d'atei. יהי רצון מלפניך ה' אלוהינו
ואלוהי אבותינו שתהא תורתך אומנותנו בעולם הזה ותהא עמנו לעולם הבא. yehi
ratzon milfanecha adonai eloheinu v'elohei avoteinu she-tehei torat'cha omanutenu ba-olam hazeh v'tehei
imanu l'olam haba. חנינא בר פפא רמי בר פפא נחמן בר פפא
אחא בר פפא אבא בר פפא
רפרם בר פפא
רכיש בר פפא סורחא בר פפא אדא בר פפא דרא בר פפא.
Chanina bar Pappa Rami bar Pappa Nachman bar Pappa Acha bar Pappa
Abba bar Pappa Rafram bar
Pappa
Rachish bar Pappa Surcha bar Pappa Adda bar Pappa Darra bar Pappa.
הערב נא ה' אלוהינו את דברי תורתך בפינו ובפיפיות עמך בית ישראל
ונהיה אנחנו וצאצאינו וצאצאי עמך בית ישראל כולנו יודעי שמך ולומדי תורתך
לשמה. ha'arev na adonai eloheinu et divrei torat'cha be-pinu u-ve-fifyot amcha beit
yisrael v'nihyeh anachnu v'tza'atza'einu v'tza'atza'ei amcha beit yisrael kulanu yodei shemecha v'lomdei
torat'cha lishmah. You can tell I've done this a few times. מאויבי
תחכמני מצותיך כי לעולם היא לי. יהי לבי תמים בחקיך למען לא
אבוש. לעולם לא אשכח פקודיך כי בם חייתני. ברוך אתה ה' למדני
חקיך. me-oyvay techakmeni mitzvotecha ki l'olam hi li. yehi libi tamim be-chukecha
l'ma'an lo evosh. l'olam lo eshkach pikudecha ki vam chiyitani. baruch atah
adonai lamdeni chukecha. אמן אמן אמן סלה ועד. amen amen amen selah
va'ed. מודים אנחנו לפניך ה' אלוהינו ואלוהי אבותינו ששמת חלקנו מיושבי בית
המדרש ולא שמת חלקנו מיושבי קרנות שאנו משכימים והם משכימים אנו משכימים
לדברי תורה והם משכימים לדברים בטלים אנו עמלים והם עמלים אנו עמלים
ומקבלים שכר והם עמלים ואינם מקבלים שכר אנו רצים והם רצים אנו
רצים לחיי העולם הבא והם רצים לבאר שחת שנאמר ואתה אלוהים תורידם
לבאר שחת אנשי דמים ומרמה לא יחצו ימיהם ואני אבטח בך. modim
anachnu lifanecha adonai eloheinu v'elohei avoteinu she-samta chelkenu mi-yoshvei beit ha-midrash v'lo
samta chelkenu mi-yoshvei keranot she-anu mashkimim v'hem mashkimim anu mashkimim l'divrei torah
v'hem mashkimim l'dvarim betelim anu amelim v'hem amelim anu amelim u-mekablim sachar
v'hem amelim v'einam mekablim sachar anu ratzim v'hem ratzim anu ratzim l'chayei
ha-olam haba v'hem ratzim l've'er shachat she-ne'emar v'atah elohim toridem l've'er shachat
anshei damim u-mirmah lo yeche-tzu yemeihem va-ani evtach bach. יהי רצון מלפניך
ה' אלוהי כשם שעזרתני לסיים מסכת סוטה כן תעזרני להתחיל מסכתות ספרים
אחרים ולסיימם ללמוד וללמד לשמור ולעשות ולהקים את כל דברי תלמוד תורתך
באהבה. yehi ratzon milfanecha adonai elohai k'shem she-azartani l'sayem masechet sotah ken
ta'azreni l'hatchil masechtot sefarim acherim u-l'sayamam lilmod u-lelamed lishmor v'la'asot u-le-kayem et
kol divrei talmud torat'cha b'ahavah. זכות כל התנאים והאמוראים ותלמידי חכמים תעמד
לנו ולזרענו שלא תמוש התורה מפינו ומפי זרענו וזרע זרענו עד עולם
ותתקיים בנו בהתהלכך תנחה אותך בשכבך תשמר עליך והקיצות היא תשיחך כי
בי ירבו ימיך ויוסיפו לך שנות חיים אורך ימים בימינה ובשמאלה עושר
וכבוד ה' עוז לעמו יתן ה' יברך את עמו בשלום. z'chut kol
ha-tanna'im v'ha-amora'im v'talmidei chachamim ta'amod lanu u-l'zar'enu she-lo tamush ha-torah mi-pinu u-mi-pi
zar'enu v'zera zar'enu ad olam v'titkayem banu be-hithalech'cha tancheh otach be-shachbecha tishmor
alecha v'hekitzota hi t'sichecha ki bi yirbu yamecha v'yosifu lach shnot chayim
orech yamim bi-yminah u-vi-smolah osher v'chavod adonai oz l'amo yitein adonai yivarech
et amo va-shalom. But we don't have a מנין, minyan, do we?
Not really. Thanks. OK. All right. Shut down guest table?
I don't know,
maybe.